# James Hogg

#### PHD STUDENT

School of Mathematical Sciences, Queensland University of Technology



■ james.hogg@hdr.qut.edu.au | ② JamieHogg-depo | 🛅 jamieahogg | 🔰 JamieAHogg

I am a statistician currently studying for a PhD in the School of Mathematical Sciences at the Queensland University of Technology (QUT). Focused on generating small area level estimates of cancer risk factors for the globally recognized Australian Cancer Atlas, my research is driven by a passion for making research more accessible, as well as a commitment to utilizing Bayesian inference and spatial modeling to enhance the field of cancer research. My teaching experience, together with the awards I've received for presentations and invited talks, attest to my proficiency in conveying complex statistical ideas to a wide audience. With my dedication to advancing the field of cancer research and a deep-seated enthusiasm for exploring the potential of Bayesian inference and spatial modeling, I am poised to make a significant contribution to either academic or industry roles.

### Research interests.

R, tidyverse, Stan
Spatio/hierarchical modelling
Bayesian inference
Spatial variation in cancer outcomes
Visualisations/mapping

### **Education and qualifications**

**Doctor of Philosophy, Statistics** 

Brisbane, Australia

2021 (ongoing)

QUEENSLAND UNIVERSITY OF TECHNOLOGY (QUT)

- Full-time equivalent
- PhD funded by the internationally-awarded Australian Cancer Atlas

### **Graduate Statistician (Gstat) Accreditation**

STATISTICAL SOCIETY OF AUSTRALIA 2021 (ongoing)

Master of Biostatistics Virtual

University of Queensland (UQ)

2018-2020

- Provided by the Biostatistics Colloboration of Australia
- GPA: 7.0
- Dean's Commendation for Academic Excellence (2018 & 2019)
- Thesis complete at Cancer Council Queensland

### **Bachelor of Music with Distinction**

Brisbane, Australia

QUEENSLAND UNIVERSITY OF TECHNOLOGY (QUT)

2015-2017

- Minor in statistics (4 units)
- GPA: 6.5
- Dean's Award for Excellence (all 6 semesters)

### **Queensland Certificate of Education**

Brisbane, Australia

2010-2014

Indooroopilly State High School

- Overall Position (OP): 1
- Best All Rounder Award 2014
- Parents and Citizens' Music Award 2014

# **Employment**

Supervisor (casual) Virtual

**ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AUTHORITY (EPA) VICTORIA** 

May 2023 - August 2023

- · Supervisory of QUT research assistant
- QUT and EPA colloboration to create a R Shiny app to visualise spatial data

Research assistant (part-time)

Virtual

DEPARTMENT OF HEALTH, WESTERN AUSTRALIA (DOHWA)

November 2022 (ongoing)

· Consulting on bayesian modelling

Instructor/presentor of Bayesian training

Perth, Australia

November 2022

DEPARTMENT OF HEALTH, WESTERN AUSTRALIA (DOHWA)

· Three days of intensive training on Bayesian spatial temporal analysis

Internship (full-time)

Virtual

DEPARTMENT OF HEALTH, WESTERN AUSTRALIA (DOHWA)

August - November 2022

· Project: Bayesian modelling

• Supervisors: Dr Susanna Cramb, Dr Alex Xiao

- Recommended spatio-temporal models for a wide range of health data
- Provided lengthy and detailed reports giving the details of spatio-temporal models
- Created detailed and large R code scrips to run a variety of models
- · Created training materials for 3-days of intensive Bayesian spatio-temporal course

Research assistant (part-time)

Brisbane, Australia

October 2021 - March 2022

September - November 2021

QUEENSLAND UNIVERSITY OF TECHNOLOGY (QUT)

• Project: Modifiable areal unit problem (MAUP) in disease mapping

• Co-investigators: Dr Susanna Cramb, Ass. Prof. Helen Thompson

Tutor (casual) Brisbane, Australia

QUEENSLAND UNIVERSITY OF TECHNOLOGY (QUT)

Course title: Quantitative Skills for Health Scientists (LQB286)

Marker (casual) Virtual

University of Queensland (UQ)

July 2021 - October 2022

Brisbane, Australia

June 2022 (ongoing)

July - November 2022

- Course title: Categorical Data and Generalised Linear Models (STAT7608)
- Course title: Regression Modelling 2 (STAT7619)
- Course title: Applied Regression Analyses (PUBH7631)

# **Professional service**

UN Datathon Brisbane, Australia

United Nations November 2023

### Co-chair of Bayesian Research and Applications group (BRAG)

QUEENSLAND UNIVERSITY OF TECHNOLOGY (QUT)

STANCONNECT 2022: STAN THROUGH SPACE AND TIME

· Organiser of fortnightly internal talks on Bayesian research

Volunteer Virtual

GOOD DATA INSTITUTE (GDI)

March - June 2023

Organiser and host Virtual

• 10 speakers from 8 countries

• Over 100 virtual attendees

**Invited session** 

Master's Thesis Virtual

Cancer Council Queensland

March - October 2020

• Title: "Influence of individual- and area-level socioeconomic factors on breast cancer stage at diagnosis: A multilevel approach"

# Selected research presentations.

#### Contributed session (planned)

Virtual

Virtual

AUSTRALIAN STATISTICAL CONFERENCE

December 2023

· Title: Solutions to sparsity in small area level survey statistics: Mapping the prevalence of cancer risk factors in Australia

Short talk

November 2023

EARLY CAREER RESEARCHER CANCER EPIDEMIOLOGY CONFERENCE

• Title: Mapping the prevalence of cancer risk factors at the small area level in Australia

Ottawa, Canada

July 2023

• Title: Advances in small area estimation for severely sparse data

The restance in critical area community of severely sparse date

Invited talk Virtual

EPIDEMIOLOGY IN GOVERNMENT (EIG) SPECIAL INTEREST GROUP (SIG) MEETING

• Title: Mapping Cancer: The Australian Cancer Atlas

Short talk Virtual

SPARSE Symposium November 2022

• Title: Risk factors and the Australian Cancer Atlas: the trepidation of instability and sparsity in small area estimation

Short talk Virtual

SECOND EARLY CAREER RESEARCHER CANCER EPIDEMIOLOGY CONFERENCE

November 2022

December 2022

· Title: Risk factors and the Australian Cancer Atlas: the trepidation of instability and sparsity in small area estimation

Poster presentation Montreal, Canada

INTERNATIONAL SOCIETY OF BAYESIAN ANALYSIS (ISBA) WORLD MEETING

June 2022

• Title: Introducing a Bayesian two-stage logistic-normal model for small area estimation of proportions

Poster presentation Montreal, Canada

THE BAYESIAN YOUNG STATISTICIANS MEETING

June 2022

· Title: Introducing a Bayesian two-stage logistic-normal model for small area estimation of proportions

Short talk QUT, Brisbane, Australia

QANZIAM CONFERENCE June 2022

• Title: Searching for stability in Bayesian small area estimation of proportions

Contributed talk Virtual

SMALL AREA ESTIMATION, SURVEYS AND DATA SCIENCE

May 2022

· Title: Searching for stability: Introducing a method of small area estimation for proportions using severely sparse data

Short talk Moreton Island, Australia

ACEMS Final Retreat

November 2021

• Title: Modelling cancer risk factors in Australia

# **Selected publications**

### arXiv preprint (2023)

J HOGG, J CAMERON, S CRAMB, P BAADE, K MENGERSEN

• A Two-stage Bayesian Small Area Estimation Method for Proportions

### arXiv preprint (2023)

J HOGG, J CAMERON, S CRAMB, P BAADE, K MENGERSEN

• Mapping the prevalence of cancer risk factors at the small area level in Australia

### Awards\_\_\_\_\_

### **Best Oral Presentation Award**

THIRD EARLY CAREER RESEARCHER CANCER EPIDEMIOLOGY CONFERENCE

November 2023

First place in Hackathon

GOOD DATA INSTITUTE (GDI)

June 2023

• Hackathon with BioGrow (NZ NFP)

2023 SuperHERO

HEALTH EQUITY RESEARCH WITH OUTCOMES April 2023

**Best Oral Presentation Award** 

SECOND EARLY CAREER RESEARCHER CANCER EPIDEMIOLOGY CONFERENCE

November 2022

**Honourable Mention for Best Student Presentation** 

QANZIAM CONFERENCE June 2022

**QUT Centre for Data Science and Cancer Council QLD Scholarship** 

Doctor of Philosophy, Statistics April 2021

• \$30,000 p.a. for 3.5 years during PhD studies.

#### **Star Graduate**

BIOSTATISTICS COLLOBORATION OF AUSTRALIA December 2020

# **Professional memberships**

Statistical Society of Australia (SSA) International Society of Bayesian Analysis (ISBA) Centre for Data Science (CDS) Health Equity Research with Outcomes (HERO)

# Software\_

Statistical: R, Python, Stata

Writing: MS Office suite, Latex, Endnote, Mendeley

Terminal: Git Bash, Unix

Bayesian computation: Stan, nimble, WinBUGS, JAGS, pymc

Productivity: Sunsama, Zoom

Visualisation: Gggplot2, Canva, Lucidchart Core R packages: tidyverse, shiny, Rmarkdown